ok guys for today's problem we've got
this epoxide and we are going to react
with methoxide in methanol, we're going
to get this product so what we need to
do is show the mechanism. if this
confusing you will want to take a look at
my lecture on epoxides and then give
this a shot.
ok guys so to draw this mechanism we
have to recall a couple things about
epoxides. number one: eooxides are very
susceptible to nucleophilic attack
because there's a lot of ring stream
from that small three-membered ring, that
means that either of these carbons could
potentially be attacked by a nucleophile
so we do have a nucleophile, we've got
methoxide, that's gonna be a good
nucleophile, so we want to ask ourselves:
which carbon is it gonna attack in the
epoxide? now sterics are going to
dictate that it is going to go over here
it is the less sterically hindered side so
it is more available for nucleophilic
attack, so if it attacks right there, it's
gonna pop open the epoxide, we're
gonna get this here, so this is the
methoxide that attacked, this used to be
the epoxide here but now that popped open
to leave the oxyanion
there and now the second step here is
kinda like the second step of Williamson
ether synthesis, except that it's
intramolecular because this oxyanion
can do an SN2 right here to kick off
this bromide and that'll lead us to the
product. and so what we can do just to
make sure we're able to draw that
properly, we can see that this is gonna
create a five-membered ring because this
oxyanion is going to attack this
carbon so that generates this
five-membered ring, and then this group
over here will still be there so there
we go we have an opening of the epoxide
followed by intramolecular ring closure.
thanks for watching, guys, subscribe to my channel for more tutorials and as always feel free to email me